[SPEAKER_00]: There's a confusion around emotions and feelings.
[SPEAKER_00]: Feelings, emotions.
[SPEAKER_00]: And people sometimes wonder, what is the Pali word for emotion?
[SPEAKER_00]: And it's... and some translators translate the word citta, the Pali word citta, as emotion.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, really?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because it's the heart.
[SPEAKER_00]: Right, right.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, my emotions.
[SPEAKER_00]: Right.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the emotional being, the mind, but... Yeah, it's a bit of a stretch.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, no, the the the emotions, I mean, based on its own
[SPEAKER_01]: Etymology just means, like, intense feeling.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, like, you're emotional.
[SPEAKER_01]: Emotionally positive, emotionally negative.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it is a kind of mind state, but on the basis of how you feel, just amplified, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_01]: But also, I think, if you if you if you were to ask psychotherapy or so on, I think things got extremely convoluted there, whereby emotions are subconscious, unconscious, physiological, and it's just like something's unconscious.
[SPEAKER_01]: How can you talk about it consciously?
[SPEAKER_01]: How can you even know it?
[SPEAKER_01]: No, it's just the amplified feelings.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you cultivate, see, your responses to feelings, you're basically cultivating an attitude of being emotional, more and more.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why you need to keep giving in to your feelings, in order to become...
[SPEAKER_01]: Eventually, then, you don't have to.
[SPEAKER_01]: Emotions will be automatic.
[SPEAKER_01]: Those mental states will be instantaneous.
[SPEAKER_01]: When touched by unpleasant feeling, or when touched by pleasant feeling, because you cultivated it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it doesn't matter the complexity of an emotion.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's always within the feeling.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's always... Oh, how is this emotional, complex, subconsciously, unconscious state felt?
[SPEAKER_01]: Consciously, it's felt pleasant.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the doorway.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the framework for any emotion, any direction you can take, and any action you can do on account of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you don't need to worry about this emotion or that emotion.
[SPEAKER_01]: You just need to see whether your actions
[SPEAKER_01]: So, for example, like the satipaṭṭhāna, he knows a lustful mind as a lustful mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you could say he knows an emotional
[SPEAKER_00]: Emotionally shaped mind?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, you could say.
[SPEAKER_01]: But basically, even that, any state of mind, it's underlined by a certain way it's felt.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you say, he knows elated mind is elated mind, depressed mind is depressed mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: How is elated mind felt?
[SPEAKER_01]: Is it elated in a positive sense or a negative sense?
[SPEAKER_01]: So, yeah, contemplation of the mind is inseparable from contemplation of the feeling, or thoughts, or the body for that matter.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why it's satipaṭṭhāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's the four foundations, like one, one and a half.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the point is...
[SPEAKER_01]: Whatever for you designation, word, term, emotion means, you just want to see past it, as in see beyond it, as how it's simultaneously felt.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's emotional.
[SPEAKER_01]: You already know whether it's pleasant or unpleasant, whether you want it to stay longer, whether you're riding the wave of pleasure, excitement, or you're basically absolutely trying to get rid of it at all costs.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're emotionally disturbed, distraught.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, just to say, I feel angry.
[SPEAKER_00]: I have the emotion.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, you can say emotion of anger.
[SPEAKER_01]: Anger.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sure.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, I'm emotionally angry.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, what do I do?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, you stop trying to get rid of the pain of that anger, of that emotion.
[SPEAKER_00]: But what about if I just am aware that I'm angry?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, I suppose that's the first step, but that won't do anything.
[SPEAKER_01]: That'll just make you aware of the anger.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, you need to become aware, self-aware of whatever you're feeling, whatever you state in.
[SPEAKER_01]: You need to become aware of the problem in order to deal the problem.
[SPEAKER_01]: But being aware of the problem does not do anything for the problem.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm aware of the problem, but I need to be more aware of the problem, so that I can actually see the way out of the problem.
[SPEAKER_01]: More often than not, that's the case, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: You need to be more aware of the problem.
[SPEAKER_01]: You need to make it a bigger... like a recognition.
[SPEAKER_01]: This is a serious problem, because otherwise you will not master enough determination, effort to keep drilling in that direction and undo it.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's easier to forget about, especially when that emotion has subsided.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's where the Buddha, the divine messenger, is something you need to reflect on.
[SPEAKER_01]: Before you get sick, before you get old, and before you're dead, you need to recognize that you are liable to be sick, liable.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm liable to lust, I'm liable to anger.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's...
[SPEAKER_01]: I need to recognize before these things occur, so basically, so I can uproot them, so they don't occur anymore.
[SPEAKER_01]: But yeah, in order to recognize that you're liable to these things, the first step is to be aware of them when they're present.
[SPEAKER_01]: But thinking that just by being aware when they're present, you're somehow dealing with it, will then not make you think about it when those things are not present.
[SPEAKER_01]: You think you're fine.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because now I'm not angry, see?
[SPEAKER_01]: But is it because you uprooted the basis for anger?
[SPEAKER_01]: But simply because the circumstances are currently soothing you, and going the way you want them to be.
[SPEAKER_00]: Now you're emotionally... you're getting emotional about that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you would still be disturbed on some account if things were to change, and they will have to change.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, what about that idea that I brought up earlier, Evers?
[SPEAKER_00]: Emotions shape the mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: Emotion is the shape of the mind, meaning that it actually constricts the mind, it clouds the mind, because it's given now a shape which is twisted and, you know, it's twisted in this particular way.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's kind of wrong.
[SPEAKER_01]: It lacks perspective.
[SPEAKER_01]: It sort of has stunted the perspective.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, by removing the root cause... For the emotion, you will then remove the root cause for the reduction of your perspective caused by the emotion.
[SPEAKER_01]: When you're emotional, you know...
[SPEAKER_00]: But if you... so, you're no longer emotional, you have a larger perspective, no more narrowed response or automatic response to how you feel.
[SPEAKER_00]: There is no shape then.
[SPEAKER_00]: That mind is no longer constricted.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well...
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, well, the mind is not only constricted, but more like you are not constricted in regards to the shape of the mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: The mind still will have some shape, for as long as the mind is there.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the certain shapes will not constrict the mind anymore.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's how you liberate your understanding.
[SPEAKER_01]: But your understanding liberates you.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, in satipaṭṭhāna, you know depressed, constricted, restricted mind, as depressed, constricted, restricted mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you are not depressed, constricted and restricted by it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like knowing the presence of hindrances, for example, that's how you understand the way out of them.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not like they never arise on the level of the body.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just whatever arises on that level of the body, like whatever is being experienced, it cannot restrict you anymore.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you know the escape... Well, yeah, because the only reason it was restricting you is because you restricted yourself by giving in to getting... trying to get rid of craving against the unpleasant feeling.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the hindrances trap you, but not by like... by their own effort.
[SPEAKER_01]: They like set up traps and you keep stepping into it, by giving in to craving against the discomfort.
[SPEAKER_01]: Craving for the comfort.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's how you trap yourself within the domain of hindrances.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's how you trap yourself within these random shapes of the mind that arise, with this random weather.
[SPEAKER_01]: Literally like weather.
[SPEAKER_01]: Mind, emotions, if you want to call it, even moods, are the weather.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sometimes it's sunny, sometimes it's hot, sometimes cold, sometimes windy, sometimes it rains.
[SPEAKER_01]: Neither of those weather
[SPEAKER_01]: Circumstances, conditions, need to be affecting how you... like, your responses, your feelings, your thoughts and what you're trying to deal with.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: It could make no difference if you go beyond it.
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't mind if it's rain.
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't mind if it's sunny.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, I remain untouched by that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, you're not excited or depressed.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't wish for rain and cry when it's too hot.
[SPEAKER_01]: Nor do I cry when it's raining and get all depressed when things are wet.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, when you experience a disagreeable thing... Hm.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just disagreeable.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't get all...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, latent mind is known as a latent mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: Depressed mind is a depressed mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: Neither latent nor depressed.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, in a sense, the having emotions... Hm.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's a symptom, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's a symptom.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you don't need to deal with that, but you need to start looking what else is there beyond it, that is the more of a problem than these emotions that are a symptom of a problem.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, what is the... like emotions, it's literally where the comes.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't stop it.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not because you've done something wrong and it started to rain.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you want to see, well, is there anything that I am doing that's responsible for me being affected by these emotions, by this weather, by these moods that come and go?
[SPEAKER_01]: And then you realize, yeah, there is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, you'll be affected by rain only when you crave for doing things on account of sunny, good weather.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you don't really mind...
[SPEAKER_01]: You will not be affected by when the weather changes, because it doesn't affect you.
[SPEAKER_01]: You were not committed to emotionally, to things you want to do, for the sake of comfort, pleasure, which require sunshine, which require good weather, which cannot be done in rain.
[SPEAKER_01]: But say, alternatively, if you're a bit tired of work, tired of people, you want rain, because that everything stops, everything goes quiet, nobody comes, nobody goes anywhere.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, then you would want to rain.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, when the sun comes, people wake up and start going left and right and coming to your place.
[SPEAKER_01]: You will not want that.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, on some occasion, the same weather makes you happy, makes you sad.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why is that?
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not because of the weather.
[SPEAKER_01]: If things were truly rooted in the weather, you would always be happy when it's a certain weather, when it's a certain shape of the mind, when it's a certain state of the mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you weren't.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you're happy based on basically where your craving has projected your expectations, pretty much.
[SPEAKER_01]: Craving rooted in how you feel and how you want to avoid feeling.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, getting emotional.
[SPEAKER_00]: It can show you in which direction you need to be questioning things.
[SPEAKER_01]: It shows you what the problem is.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're liable to emotions.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, you have a problem.
[SPEAKER_01]: Emotions would not have arisen without the necessary basis of presently enduring craving for that, against, or for that certain feeling that's there.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, let's say...
[SPEAKER_01]: If you got emotional, that can only be done on the level of... it can be done on the basis of you craving against this pleasure or pleasure.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're craving for pleasure.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, once that craving is removed or diminished...
[SPEAKER_01]: Diminished.
[SPEAKER_01]: Gradually, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Gradually diminished.
[SPEAKER_01]: You'll be less and less emotional.
[SPEAKER_01]: You'll be cooling down.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So... You can't be emotional, by the way, without having passion.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you can regard emotions as a symptom, or you can regard a passion as a symptom.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you can say, if there is craving in regard to how you're feeling, whatever you're feeling at the time, present and enduring, there is passion, there is emotion.
[SPEAKER_01]: To what extent?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, that's determined by the extent of your ignorance of your own craving.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's determined by the extent you took your own feelings for granted, as something to be wished for, delighted in, or something to be resisted, and got rid of.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, so for... like being emotion... emotionless seems to be... yeah, that's probably a fear of most.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, you don't just want to be depressed, looking... Well, yeah, because from their point of view... ...dead inside.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, the idea... any idea of emotionlessness is judged by, is discerned, is discriminated against the background of what they know, which is emotions.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, from the point of view of emotions, it's like... it feels like... from the point of view of passion, being passion-free, passionless, it's like... well, that's like death from the point of view of passion.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it is from the point of view of passion.
[SPEAKER_00]: That is who you are.
[SPEAKER_01]: It is death of the passion which you are.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's death of you.
[SPEAKER_01]: The way you know yourself.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you have a choice.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can either practice towards the death of passion, or you can stay out of fear, not go there, and then be liable to everything else that passion is basically direct cause of.
[SPEAKER_01]: The entire saṃsara of suffering, liability, torment, despair, lamentation, death, the real death.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, because you're afraid to die,
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you're afraid to let your passions and emotions die, you're bound to actually die.
[SPEAKER_01]: You bind yourself to death.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you're afraid of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because that's how you reach deathless, as the Buddha would say.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's how death does not apply to you anymore.
[SPEAKER_00]: By extinguishing passions and emotions.
It's not like that.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you should not act out of your emotions.
[SPEAKER_00]: You should not act out of emotions.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, that's the first step.
[SPEAKER_01]: You should not act out of emotions.
[SPEAKER_01]: You should become aware of them, while they're enduring, especially.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's how you don't act out of them.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you should also see them as a symptom of an underlying problem.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you're not going to see that... Not think that, oh, like, just being aware of it and enduring it somehow, I'm dealing with it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because they were not a problem.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you think that the symptoms are the problem, you're not going to look for what the real problem is, the cause of these symptoms.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, pretty much, unless you're free from suffering, unless you understood the Four Noble Truths and became Sotāpanna, everything you think is a problem, is really a symptom of a problem.
[SPEAKER_00]: Right.
[SPEAKER_01]: Again, when you suffer, suffering is a symptom of liability to suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because that's what the problem is.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why you suffer in the first place, because you were liable to suffer.
[SPEAKER_00]: Right.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's dukkha.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what dukkha is, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: The symptoms of that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Suffering is the symptom of dukkha.
[SPEAKER_01]: And dukkha is the problem.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, freedom from dukkha then means freedom from symptoms of dukkha, which is freedom from suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's an unfortunate translation.
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, it kind of... yeah, you could say that because symptoms of suffering... symptoms of dukkha are suffering, dukkha is also suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sure.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's not on the same level.
[SPEAKER_01]: Dukkha, that needs to be understood,
[SPEAKER_01]: I am subject to suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm subject to misfortune.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, nothing has happened to me, but it could.
[SPEAKER_01]: I am subjected to the possibility of these things happening.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm a prey to suffering, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if people just confuse dukkha to be the suffering that's just felt, sometimes felt, sometimes isn't, they're not looking for what the real problem is.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, literally, then, the problem is only when you're being attacked by a lion.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't recognize that the problem is that the lion can pounce on you at any given time.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's already the problem.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's the only reason why the lion eventually did attack you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you remained within the lion's boundaries, where the lion hunts.
[SPEAKER_01]: But see, even before the lion attacks you, if you recognize that this is the hunting ground of a lion, means I am liable to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: I better do something about it before lion attacks me.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what dukkha is.
[SPEAKER_01]: That recognition of that.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, literally, dukkha means unease.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like sukha means ease.
[SPEAKER_01]: Dukkha is the opposite.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's dis-ease, unease.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's exactly...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, there's nothing wrong with me.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm not being mauled by a lion, yet.
[SPEAKER_01]: But I recognize that this is literally the stomping ground of wild cats that hunt people.
[SPEAKER_01]: I am prey to that.
[SPEAKER_01]: The recognition of that will make you very uneasy.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's much easier to just ignore that, because anxiety, fear, dread... Oh, how do I deal with this?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you can't just hide, because you're still within the same hunting ground.
[SPEAKER_01]: You have to step outside eventually, and you still step outside into the area where they will kill you.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's easier to ignore, then, that... that anxious recognition of that uneasiness, that you are prey to suffering of any kind, and then just focus on the present moment, whatever's presently arisen, and with wishful thinking, that everything will work out.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, literally, then, you wait for things to arise in order to practice.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, I'm feeling this right now.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, the feeling has come.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now the feeling has passed away.
[SPEAKER_01]: As if passing away the feeling meant you dealt with it somehow.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: It means, okay, so you evaded an attack of a lion.
[SPEAKER_01]: Does that mean now you're not liable to another attack?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you were attacked by a lion, you got away, you recognized that that was suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: Got away, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you keep evading, evading, evading.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you say, well, I don't suffer as much.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: I must be... Yeah, I became very skilled in hiding away from a lion.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, but the only reason you have to do that is because you're still within the lion's grounds.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the Buddha's practice takes you out of the dukkha, takes you out of the lion's grounds.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, you don't need to... that's true burden.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, see, you might be skillful at evading the lion, but you're constantly burdened by the duty of... you need to hide.
[SPEAKER_01]: One slip, one error, you're done.
[SPEAKER_01]: And, bottom line is, deep down, you know, eventually, it will have to get you.
[SPEAKER_01]: It will get you.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the divine messengers.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sickness, aging, you can't hide from that.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can hide from everything else in between, semi-successfully.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if your practice never makes you realize, oh, it's about liability to suffering, being prey to suffering, as the Buddha would say, you're not practicing.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're just managing.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's not the practice.
[SPEAKER_01]: Practice uproots things.
[SPEAKER_01]: Practice doesn't manage.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, yeah, so...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the fact that you go throughout your day without experiencing much lust, without experiencing much anger, without experiencing much suffering of any kind,
[SPEAKER_01]: It means nothing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Is it because you have stepped outside of the domain, where you were a prey to these things?
[SPEAKER_01]: As in, is it because it's impossible for you to suffer, because you're not liable to future lust, aversion, delusion, or it's simply because circumstances suit you?
[SPEAKER_01]: Which one is it?
[SPEAKER_01]: And if you look at it honestly, you already know the answer.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's easy to think that, well, see, since I discovered Buddhism, I don't suffer as much.
[SPEAKER_01]: But why is that?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because I understood the nature of that dis-ease, that uneasy, that pray to suffering of any kind.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or because, you know, I'm a bit more careful in what I do or say, practice restraint and live in this protected spiritual community or the environment.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which one is it?
[SPEAKER_01]: So, am I internally free from suffering or just external, have external buffer zones?
[SPEAKER_01]: And again, if you're honest, the answer will be quite simple and obvious.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's already there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because if you know internally that you're free, you're an outsider, you know how to escape the domain of lying.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not even a specific lying.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why would you worry about specific lying, which might jump on you, when you don't live where the lions hunt?
[SPEAKER_00]: So, keeping that image of lying, being inside the lying enclosure, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you can...
[SPEAKER_01]: Game reserve.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you can describe all the ways that a lion can maul you, or the lion can catch you, and you can recognize all the different ways that you can suffer.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you can feel enriched on account of it, but fundamentally nothing has changed.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're still...
[SPEAKER_01]: It doesn't matter if you know which... how many ways lions can sort of drag you around and kill you.
[SPEAKER_01]: The point is you're still liable and you're going to... and subjected.
[SPEAKER_01]: To the possibility of one of those ways applying to you.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's not about study, studying the ways you can suffer.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's about recognizing that you can suffer, full stop, on account of any way.
[SPEAKER_01]: See, what is... That's why dhamma is the nature of things.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not this specific manifestation of that, that's within the nature.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you want to understand how to be free from these things, you need to understand the nature of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, what is the nature of you being a prey to lions hunting?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, the nature is that you are within the lion's domain.
[SPEAKER_01]: Can lions get you if you're not within their enclosure?
[SPEAKER_01]: If you're outside of their game reserve?
[SPEAKER_01]: If you abandon it?
[SPEAKER_01]: If you freed yourself from it?
[SPEAKER_01]: If you broke away?
[SPEAKER_01]: Impossible for lions to hunt you down.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, why are you in that enclosure?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, because you don't recognize that you are prey to suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't recognize that you're a prey.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you don't recognize that you're a prey, because that's... it freaks people out, when you recognize that.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why people would freak out, when the Buddha would teach them, and the minds were not ready.
[SPEAKER_00]: But rec... so, recognizing that you are a prey... Basically, ignoring what the real problem is.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why you remain under that problem.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the problem is that you are liable to suffering, not what specifically, or on account of what specific thing you suffer.
[SPEAKER_00]: But... but understand that you somehow...
[SPEAKER_00]: How can you no longer be a prey?
[SPEAKER_00]: How can you no longer be a prey to the lion?
[SPEAKER_01]: How can you no longer be?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, by understanding, like, what the extent of the lion's domain.
[SPEAKER_01]: Understanding the extent of the dukkha, you will understand what the freedom from that, what the escape from that dukkha is.
[SPEAKER_01]: So then, the the truth that you will discover, the four noble truths, basically, but let's keep with the simile, would be, oh, the only reason
[SPEAKER_01]: The lions can hunt you down and will eventually, is because you yourself keep yourself in that game reserve.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you keep yourself there because you... Well, because you value pleasures that you get there.
[SPEAKER_01]: You know, it has nice fruits.
[SPEAKER_01]: Good company.
[SPEAKER_00]: Beautiful views.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Adventure.
[SPEAKER_01]: Lovely streams.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whatever basically gets you going, it has it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But at the same time, it has lions that are stalking you and hunting you down.
[SPEAKER_01]: So...
[SPEAKER_00]: So, no longer...
[SPEAKER_01]: If you were to not forget that there are lions might be watching you at any given time, no amount of these joyful pleasures that that game deserve can offer, will be enough for you to stay there.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, what happens is, most of the time, you don't see the lions.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you afford to forget that you are still a prey to the lions, even if you don't see them.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, by affording to forget that, you then afford to be attracted and appreciate all these beauties of senses that you can get from that game result.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it's literally forgetting that you're liable to death.
[SPEAKER_01]: Maraṇasati, it's exactly that.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't see death, so you don't think about it.
[SPEAKER_01]: By not thinking about it, you maintain the whole world of sensuality, anger, despair, everything else.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you were not to forget that you're liable to die at any given second, and in-breath, out-breath, as the Buddha would say, any attraction you have on account of being alive, any passion, will have to disappear.
[SPEAKER_01]: Eventually, it will wither away, because you're not maintaining it anymore.